26 IT'S MOTHER!" Their belief in the Magic was an abiding thing. After the morning's
incantations colins sometimes gave them Magic lectures. "I like to do it," he explained,
"because when I grow up and make great scientific discoveries I shall be
obliged to lecture about them and so this is practice I can only give short
lectures now because I am very young, and besides Ben Weatherstaff would feel as
if he was in church and he would go to sleep the best thing about lecturing
said Ben, "is that a chap can get up and say what he pleases and no other chap
can answer him back. I wouldn't be Ain lecturing a bit myself
sometimes." But when Colin held forth under his tree old Ben fixed devouring
eyes on him and kept them there. He looked him over with critical
affection. It was not so much the lecture which interested him as the legs which
looked straighter and stronger each day, the boyish head which held itself up so
well, the once sharp chin and hollow cheeks which had filled and rounded out
and the eyes which had begun to hold the light he remembered in another
pair. Sometimes when Colin felt Ben's earnest gaze meant that he was much
impressed he wondered what he was reflecting on and once when he had
seemed quite entranced he questioned him.
"What are you thinking about, Ben weather staff he asked.
"I was thinking answered Ben, "as I'd warrant that's gone up three or 4 pound
this week. I was looking at their carves and their shoulders. I'd like to get thee
on a pair of scales." "It's the Magic and— —and Mrs Sour's
buns and milk and things," said Colin. "You see the scientific experiment has
succeeded." That morning Dickon was too late to hear the lecture. When he came he
was ruddy with running and his funny face face looked more twinkling than
usual. As they had a good deal of weeding to do after the rains they fell to work.
They always had plenty to do after a warm deep sinking rain. The moisture
which was good for the flowers was also good for the weeds which thrust up tiny
blades of grass and points of leaves which must be pulled up before their roots took too firm
hold. Colin was as good at weeding as anyone in these days and he could
lecture while he was doing doing it. "The Magic works best when you work yourself,"
he said this morning. "You can feel it in your bones and muscles. I am going to
read books about bones and muscles, but I am going to write a book about Magic I'm
making it up now. I keep finding out things." It was not very long after he had
said this that he laid down his Trel and stood up on his
feet. He had been silent for several minutes and they had seen that he was
thinking out lectures, as he often did. When he dropped his Trel and stood
upright it seemed to Mary and Dickon as if a sudden strong thought had made him
do it. He stretched himself out to his tallest height and he threw out his arms
exultantly. Color glowed in his face and his strange eyes widened with
joyfulness. All at once he had realized something to the full. "Mary! Dickon!" he
cried. "Just look at me!" They stopped their weeding and looked
at him. "Do you remember that first morning you brought me in here?" he
demanded. Dickon was looking at him very hard. Being an animal charmer he could
see more things than most people could and many of them were things he never
talked about. He saw some of them now in this
boy I that we do," he answered. Mary looked hard too, but she said
nothing. "Just this minute," said Colin, "all at once I remembered it myself— —when I
looked at my hand digging with the Trel
and I had to stand up on my feet to see
if it was real. And it is real! I'm well
—I'm well I that that art!" said Dickon. "I'm well! I'm well!" said Colin again, and his
face went quite red all over. He had known it before in a way, he had hoped it
and felt it and thought about it, but just at that minute something had rushed
all through him— —a sort of rapturous belief and realization and it had been
so strong that he could not help calling out. "I shall live forever and ever and
ever!" he cried grandly. "I shall find out thousands and thousands of things. I
shall find out about people and creatures and every everything that
grows— —like Dicken and I shall never stop making Magic. I'm well! I'm well! I feel— —I
feel as if I want to shout out something— —something thankful,
joyful!" Ben Weatherstaff, who had been working near a rosebush glanced round at
him thou might sing the Doxology," he suggested in his driest
grunt. He had no opinion of the Doxology and he did not make the suggestion with
any particular reverence. But Colin was of an exploring mind and he knew nothing about the
Doxology. "What is that?" he inquired. "Dickon can sing it for thee, I'll warrant,"
replied Ben weather staff Dickon answered with his all perceiving animal
Charmers smile. "They sing it at church," he said. "Mother says she believes the
Skylock sings it when they gets up in the morning If she says that, it must be a
nice song," Colin answered. I've never been in a church myself. I was always too ill.
Sing it, Dickon. I want to hear it." Dickon was quite simple and unaffected about it.
He understood what Colin felt better than Colin did himself. He understood by
a sort of instinct so natural that he did not know it was understanding. He
pulled off his cap and looked round still smiling they must take off their cap," he
said to Colin and so th Ben and them stand up there
nose Colin took off his cap and the sun shone on and warmed his thick hair as he
watched Dickon intently. Ben Weatherstaff scrambled up from his knees and Beed his head too
with a sort of puzzled half resentful look on his old face as if he didn't
know exactly why he was doing this remarkable thing Dickens stood out out among the
trees and rose bushes and began to sing in quite a simple matter of factact way
and in a nice strong boy voice Praise God from whom all blessings flow, Praise
Him all creatures here below, Praise Him above ye Heavenly Host, Praise Father, Son,
and Holy Ghost.
Amen." When he had finished, Ben weather staff was standing quite still with his
jaws set obstinately but with a disturbed look in his eyes fixed on
Colin. Colin's face was thoughtful and appreciative. "It is a very nice song," he
said. "I like it. Perhaps it means just what I mean when I want to shout out
that I am thankful to the Magic." He stopped and thought in a puzzled
way. "Perhaps they are both the same thing.
How can we know the exact names of everything? Sing it again, Dickon. Let us
try, Mary. I want to sing it, too. It's my song. How does it begin? 'Praise God from
whom all blessings flow And they sang it again, and Mary and
Colin lifted their voices as musically as they could and Dickens swelled quite
loud and beautiful— —and at the second line Ben weather staff raspingly cleared
his throat and at the third he joined in with such vigor that it seemed almost
savage and when the "Amen" came to an end Mary observed that the very same thing
had happened to him which had happened when he found out that Colin was not a
his chin was twitching and he was staring and winking and his leathery old cheeks were
wet. "I never seed no sense in the Doxology a four he said hely but I may
change my mind in time. I should say they'd gone up5 this week Mr Colin— —five
on them Colin was looking across the garden at something attracting his
attention and his expression had become a startled one. "Who is coming in here?" he said
quickly. "Who is it?" The door in the ivied wall had been pushed gently open and a
woman had entered. She had come in with the last line of their song and she had
stood still listening and looking at them. With the ivy behind her, the
sunlight drifted through the trees and dappling her long blue cloak, and her
nice fresh face smiling across the greenery she was rather like a softly
colored illustration in one of Colin's books. She had wonderful affectionate
eyes which seemed to take everything in— —all of them, even Ben weather STA and the
"creatures" and every flower that was in bloom. Unexpectedly as she had appeared,
not one of them felt that she was an intruder at all dickens's eyes lighted like
lamps. "It's Mother— —that's who it is!" he cried and he went across the grass at a
run. Colin began to move toward her, too, and Mary went with him. They both felt
their pulses beat faster. "It's Mother!" Dickon said again when they met
halfway I know that wanted to see her and I told her where the door was
hid." Colin held out his hand with a sort of flushed royal shyness but his eyes
quite devoured her face. "Even when I was ill I wanted to see
you," he said, "you and Dickon in the secret garden. I'd never wanted to see anyone or anything
before." The sight of his uplifted face brought about a sudden change in her own.
She flushed and the corners of her mouth shook and a mist seemed to sweep over her
eyes hey dear lad!" she broke out tremulously hey dear
lad!" as if she had not known she were going to say it. She did not say master
Colin," but just "dear lad" quite suddenly. She might have said it to
Dickon in the same way if she had seen something in his face which touched her.
Colin liked it. "Are you surprised because I am so well?" he asked. She put her hand
on his shoulder and smiled the mist out of her
eyes I that I am!" she said; "but that so like thy mother that made my heart jump."
"Do you think," said Colin a little awkwardly, "that will make my father like
me I for sure, dear lad," she answered and she gave his shoulder a soft quick
pat Ean come home Eon come home." "Susan sour be said Ben weather
staff getting close to her. "Look at the lad's legs wil th They was like
drumsticks his stocking 2 months ago and I heard folk tell as they was bandy and
nocne both at the same time. Look at them now!" Susan sby laughed a comfortable
laugh. "They're going to be fine strong lad's legs in a bit," she said. "Let him go
on playing and working in the garden and eating hearty and drinking plenty of
good sweet milk and there'll not be a finer pair of Yorkshire, thank God for it."
She put both hands on Mistress Mary's shoulders and looked her little face
over in a motherly fashion and thee, too!"
she said that grown near as hearty as our Elizabeth Ellen. I'll warrant th like
thy mother too ah Martha told me as Mrs.
Medlock heard she was a pretty woman thou be like a blush rose when thou
grows up, my little lass, bless thee." She did not mention that when Martha came
home on her "day out" and described the plain sow child she had said that she
had no confidence whatever in what Mrs.
Medlock had heard. "It doesn't stand to reason that a pretty woman could be the mother of such
a fool little lass," she had added obstinately. Mary had not had time to pay
much attention to her changing face. She had only known that she looked "different"
and seemed to have a great steal more hair and that it was growing very fast.
But remembering her pleasure in looking at the me Sahib in the past she was glad
to hear that she might someday look like her. Susan saby went round their garden
with them and was told the whole story of it and shown every bush and tree
which had come alive. Colin walked on one side of her
and Mary on the other. Each of them kept looking up at her comfortable rosy face
see secretly curious about the delightful feeling she gave them— —a sort of warm, supported
feeling. It seemed as if she understood them as Dickon understood his
"creatures." She stooped over the flowers and talked about them as if they were
children suot followed her and once or twice CED at her and flew upon her
shoulder as if it were Dickens When they told her about the robin and the first
flight of the young ones she laughed a motherly little mellow laugh in her
throat. "I suppose learning them to fly is like learning children to walk, but I'm
feared I should be all in a worr if mine had wings instead of legs," she
said. It was because she seemed such a wonderful woman in her nice Morland
cottage way that at last she was told about the Magic. "Do you believe in Magic?" asked in
after he had explained about Indian fakers I do hope you
do." "That I do, lad," she answered. "I never knowed it by that name but what does the
name matter? I warrant they call it a different name in France and a different
one in Germany the same thing has set the seeds swelling and the Sunshine and
made thee a well lad and it's the Good Thing. It isn't like us poor fools think
it matters if us is called out of our names the Big Good Thing doesn't stop to
wor it bless thee. It goes on making worlds by the million— —worlds like us.
Never these stop Believing in the Big Good Thing and knowing the worlds full
of it and call it what the likes th W singing to it when I come into the
garden." "I felt so joyful," said Colin, opening his beautiful strange eyes at
her. "Suddenly I felt how different I was— —how strong my arms and legs were, you
know— —and how I could dig and stand— —and I jumped up and wanted to shout out
something to anything that would listen the Magic listened when they sung
the Doxology. It would have listened to anything that sung. It was the joy that
mattered. Eh! lad, lad— —what's names to the Joy Maker," and she gave his shoulders a quick
soft pat again. She had packed a basket which held a regular feast this morning, and when
the hungry hour came and Dicken brought it out from its hiding place, she sat
down with them under their tree and watched them devour their food, laughing
and quite gloating over their appetites. She was full of fun and made
them laugh at all sorts of odd things.
She told them stories in broad Yorkshire and taught them new
words. She laughed as if she could not help it when they told her of the
increasing difficulty there was in pretending that Colin was still a fretful
invalid. "You see we can't help laughing nearly all the time when we are together,"
explained Colin. "And it doesn't sound ill at all. We try to choke it back but it
will burst out and that sounds worse than ever." "There's one thing that comes into
my mind so often," said Mary, "and I can scarcely ever hold in when I think of it
suddenly. I keep thinking suppose Colin's face should get to look like a full moon.
It isn't like one yet but he gets a tiny bit fatter every day— —and suppose some
morning it should look like one— —what should we
do!" "Bless us all, I can see there has a
good bit of play acting to do," said Susan sby But thou won't have to keep it up
much longer Master Craven will come home." "Do you think he will?" asked
Colin. "Why?" Susan sby chuckled softly. "I suppose it you I break thy
heart if he found out before thou told him in their own way," she said thus laid
awake nights plan in it." "I couldn't bear anyone else to tell
him," said Colin. "I think about different ways every
day. I think now I just want to run into his
room." "That'd be a fine start for him," said Susan saby I'd like to see his face, lad.
I would that hean come back— —that he One of the things they talked of was
the visit they were to make to her cottage. They planned it all. They were to
drive over the mo and lunch out of doors among the heather. They would see all the
12 children and dickens's garden and would not come back until they were
tired. Susan saby got up at last to return to the house and Mrs.
Medlock. It was time for Colin to be wheeled back
also. But before he got into his chair he stood quite close to Susan and fixed his
eyes on her with a kind of bewildered adoration and he suddenly caught hold of
the fold of her blue cloak and held it fast. "You are just what I— —what I wanted,"
he said. "I wish you were my mother— —as well as
Dickens All at once Susan sour be bent down and and drew him with her warm arms
close against the bosom under the blue cloak— —as if he had been Dickon's
brother. The quick mist swept over her
eyes hey dear lad!" she said. "Thy own mother's in this very garden, I do
believe. She couldn't keep out of it. Thy father man come back to thee
heon CHAPTER 27